A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007)
Library of Virginia
- Series III. Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007., Extent: 6.83 cubic feet (21 boxes) and 2166 emails. (Box 22-39)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries G. Rich Brusca, 2007., Extent: 3.33 cu. ft. (boxes 33-39)
    - Final Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel Given to the Governor (August 2007) (File 2) (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Final Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel Given to the Governor (August 2007) (File 3) (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 1) (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 2) (part one) (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 2) (part two) (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 3) (part one) (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 3) (part two) (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 3) (part three) (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 4) (part one) (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Draft Chapters of Report (August 2007) (File 4) (part two) (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries H. Anne Kim, July-October 2007., Extent: 109 emails
    The files of Anne Kim, Skadden, contain 109 emails sent and received between July and October 2007. There is one confidential email that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Kim's unrestricted email is accessible online.
    Email subjects include: news articles and comments on chapter drafts.
    Email correspondents include: Richard Brusca, Neil Canfield, Amy Sabrin and Michael Tierney.
- Series IV. Files of the Office of the Governor, 2007-2009., Extent: 1.40 cubic feet (4 boxes). (Box 54-57)
  The Files of the Office of the Governor series primarily document the implementation of the settlement agreements between the Commonwealth and the families and the revision of the Panel report by TriData in 2009. The majority of these records appear to be from Marc Follmer. Follmer was Deputy Director, Department of General Services (January 2006-2007), Deputy Assistant to the Governor, Office of Commonwealth Preparedness (2007-2009) and Senior Advisor to the Governor (2009-January 2010). He also was a member of the Virginia Tech Working Group, a group of Kaine administration officials tasked to address all issues related to the aftermath of the shooting and assisted in implementing the settlement agreements. Additional records related to the Virginia Tech Working Group, the settlement agreements, and the revision of the Panel report can be found in the Kaine administration email collection.
  In April 2008, the Commonwealth reached an $11 million financial settlement with 24 families of students and faculty who were killed or injured during the Virginia Tech shooting. The Commonwealth agreed to provide monetary pay outs, medical care and information on the shooting in exchange for the families to waive their rights to sue. Funds created by the settlement include: Direct Payments to Claimants, Special Damages Fund-Medical Reimbursements, Special Damages Fund-Health Insurance Fund, Public Purpose Funds-Charitable Purposes Fund, and Public Purpose Funds-Hardship Fund. Two families who filed claims against the state did not accept the settlement and filed a civil suit in 2009. The discovery of Cho's Cook Counseling Center records in July 2009 and other concerns by family members about the Panel's timeline for 16 April 2007, lead to calls for the Panel to reconvene. Kaine did not reconvene the Panel but agreed to have the report revised to reflect the new details that surfaced since 2007. Governor Kaine asked the victims' families and Virginia Tech to submit any corrections or additions they thought important by the end of August 2009. The time was extended into September after the discovery of Cho's missing Cook Counseling Center records. The first addendum was completed by TriData in November 2009. Additional corrections to the addendum were made in December 2009.
  Notable documents include: background and credentials of TriData including a copy of their 2003 assessment of Virginia's response to Hurricane Isabel (b54, f1); memorandum from Larry Roberts, Counselor to the Governor, to Governor Kaine and Chief of Staff Bill Leighty, dated 19 April 2007, providing his thoughts on how to structure the independent commission to review the shootings at Virginia Tech (b54, f2); 26 April 2007 letter retaining TriData, division of System Planning Corporation to assist the Virginia Tech Review Panel (b54, f2); copy of letter, dated 1 June 2007, appointing Skadden Arps Slate Meagher and Flom LLP as special counsel to the Virginia Tech Review Panel (b54, f2); letter from Mark Rubin, Counselor to the Governor, to Philip Schaenman, President of TriData, dated 17 August 2009, retaining the firm to revise and make corrections to the 2007 Virginia Tech Review Panel report (b54, f2); copy of settlement agreement, June 2008 (b54, f4); charts describing the name, purpose, and amounts of funds authorized under the Virginia Tech Settlement Agreement (b54, f9); Drafts of Memorandum (with supporting documentation) to Governor Kaine from Marc Follmer on Virginia Tech Outstanding Issues, March-May 2009 (b55, f4); Meeting with Governor Kaine and Virginia Tech Families, 26 September 2009 (b55, f11-12); Proposed Corrections to the Virginia Tech Panel Report, 2009 (b56, f9); Marc Follmer's notes from conference and telephone calls with Virginia Tech Review Panel members, staff from TriData and family members, September-November 2009 (b56, f10); Family Supplement to Addendum -"Forever in Our Hearts: Mass Shooting at Virginia Tech - Supplement to the Report of the Review Panel," December 2009 (b57, f3); and Virginia Tech Police Chief Wendell Flinchum's presentation to the Virginia Tech Families (b57, f5).
  - TriData, 2003, 2007, and 2009. (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007 and 2009. (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Comments and Presentations, Second Public Meeting of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, 21 May 2007. (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Settlement Agreement-Funds
    - Settlement Agreement, 2008. (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Governor Authorization of Accounts and Payments per settlement, 2008-2009. (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Local Government Investment Pool (LGIP), 2008. (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Funding Mechanism, 2009. (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Department of Treasury, Authorized Signature Forms, Virginia Tech Settlement Agreements, 2008. (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Monetary Commitment Charts, 2008-2009. (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Special Damages-Medical Reimbursement
      - List of claimants and family members eligible for reimbursement for mental health/medical expenses, 2008. (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - Virginia Criminal Injuries Compensation Fund (CICF), 2008. (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - Virginia Department of Criminal Justice Services (DCJS) Process-Reimbursement of Medical Care and/or Mental Health Treatment Expenses, 2008. (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - Release form for CICF claim file - draft language, undated. (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Special Damages Fund -Health Insurance, 2008. (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Charitable Purposes Fund (Virginia Tech Victims Family Outreach Foundation, Inc.), 2009. (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Hardship Fund, undated. (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Settlement Agreement - Miscellaneous
    - The McGammon Group Invoice, 2008. (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Meeting with Virginia Tech Families, Background Memorandum to Governor Kaine from Larry Roberts, 21 November 2008. (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Decision Brief - Transfer of funds to pay claims from the Virginia Tech Settlement, 26 February 2009. (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Drafts of Memorandum (with supporting documentation) to Governor Kaine from Marc Follmer on Virginia Tech Outstanding Issues, March-May 2009. (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Notes of Marc Follmer, 2008-2009 and undated. (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Litigation (Peterson and Pryde Claims), 2009. (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Kevin Sterne, 2008-2009. (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Larry Roberts Engagement Letter, 6 May 2009. (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Tech Board of Visitors Letter to Families (draft), June 2009. (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - James W. Morris, Disputed Settlement Fee, 2008-2009. (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - Meeting with Governor Kaine and Virginia Tech Families, 26 September 2009 (Mark Rubin?). (Box 55, Folder 11)
    - Meeting with Governor Kaine and Virginia Tech Families, 6 September 2009 (includes follow up items) (Marc Follmer?). (Box 55, Folder 12)
  - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 55, Folder 14)
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 55, Folder 15)
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Marc Follmer's undated notes on the Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Tech Review Panel Internal Working Group, 2007. (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Virginia University and College's response to the recommendations in the Virginia Tech Report, 2007. (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Documents related to the recommendations in the Virginia Tech Report, 2007 and undated. (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Addendum to Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, 2009
    - Amendment to Panel Report - Marc Follmer's notes from telephone calls with Tri-Data/Skadden, May 2009. (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Discovery of Seung Hui Cho's Cook Counseling Center case file, July-August 2009. (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - TriData Contract, August 2009. (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Proposed Corrections to the Virginia Tech Panel Report, 2009. (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Marc Follmer's notes from conference and telephone calls with Virginia Tech Review Panel members, staff from TriData and family members, September-November 2009. (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Drafts of additions and corrections to Virginia Tech Panel Report, September, November 2009 and undated. (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Office of the Inspector General for Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Investigation of April 16, 2007 (OIG Report 140-07 and OIG Report 179-09), 2007 and 2009. (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Addendum to Timeline, December 2009. (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Family Supplement to Addendum - "Forever in Our Hearts: Mass Shooting at Virginia Tech - Supplement to the Report of the Review Panel," December 2009. (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Meeting Notes from Governor Tim Kaine's meeting with Virginia Tech Families, 23 June 2007. (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Open Issues, 2009. (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, 2007 and 2009. (Box 57, Folder 6)
- Series V. Freedom of Information Act Request, 2007., Extent: 4.73 cubic feet (14 boxes). (Box 40-53)
  This series contains records copied in response to a Freedom of Information Act Request for Panel records in August 2007 (probably by the Washington Post). TriData and/or Skadden reviewed the 17 oversized boxes of Panel records in order to comply with the FOIA request. The order of these records roughly corresponds to Series I-III.